crocha@ucsd.edu crocha700.github.io github: crocha700 vimeo: crocha700 ORCID: 0000-0003-4063-5468 01 Mar, 2016

Cesar B Rocha

Physical oceanographer

Research Physical oceanography, particularly the dynamics of unsteady mesoscale to submesocale flows, and the Brazil Current System. Geophysical fluid dynamics, particularly stirring and mixing in geophysical turbulence. Numerical methods, specifically Galerkin approximations. Data science and oceanographic big data.

Education

Current, PhD in Oceanography, University of California, San Diego 2013 MSc in Oceanography, University of São Paulo, Brazil 2011, BSc in Oceanography, University of São Paulo, Brazil

Experience

2015, Fellow in Geophysical Fluid Dynamics, GFD Program, WHOI Coupled reduced equations for strongly stratified flows.

2013–Current, Graduate Student Researcher, SIO/UCSD Stratified planetary turbulence and dynamics of the upper ocean.

2012, **Visiting student**, **University of Massachusetts Dartmouth** Quasigeostrophic modes and surface quasigeostrophic solutions.

2011–2013, **Master Student**, **University of Sao Paulo** Energetics and dynamics of the Brazil Current System.

Publications

In preparation

- 2. Ardhuin, F., Rascle, N., Chapron, B., Gula, J., Molemaker, J., Gille, S., Menemenlis, D., **Rocha, C. B.**: Small scale currents have large effects on dominant ocean waves, to be submitted to GRL.
- 1. Chereskin, T. K., Gille, S. T., Rocha, C. B.: Wave-vortex decomposition in the Southern California Current System, to be submitted to JPO.

Peer-reviewed

- 4. **Rocha, C. B.**; Chereskin, T. K.; Gille, S. T. and Menemenlis, D., 2016: "Mesoscale to submesoscale wavenumber spectra in Drake Passage", *J. Phys. Oceanogr.*, 46 (2), 601-620, doi:10.1175/JPO-D-15-0087.1.
- 3. **Rocha, C. B.**; Young, W. R. and Grooms, I., 2016: "On Galerkin approximations of the surface-active quasi-geostrophic equations", *J. Phys. Oceanogr.*, 46 (1), 125-139, doi:10.1175/JPO-D-15-0073.1
- 2. **Rocha, C. B.**; da Silveira, I. C. A., Castro, B. ,M. and Lima, J. A. M., **2014**: "Vertical structure, energetics and dynamics of the Brazil Current System at 22°S-28°S", *J. Geophys. Res.*, *119*, doi:10.1002/2013JC009143.
- 1. Rocha, C. B.; Tandon, A.; da Silveira, I. C. A. and Lima, J. A. M., 2013: "Traditional Quasi-geostrophic modes and Surface Quasi-geostrophic solutions in the Southwestern Atlantic", *J. Geophys. Res.*, 118 (5), doi:10.1002/jgrc.20214.

Grey literature

1. Rocha, C. B., 2015: Coupled reduced equations for strongly stratified flows, Proceedings of the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Program, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, Woods Hole, MA.

Invited Seminars

1. Oceans and Cryosphere Seminar Series, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Fall 2015

Software

- 2. Core developer for "Python quasigeostrophic model" (PyQG), doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.30517
- 1. Core developer for "Spectral Analysis in Python" (PySpec), doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.31596

Service

2016, Reviewer for DSR-I.

2016, Representative of physical oceanography curricular group students in the student committee for faculty search in "large scale observational physical oceanography". The student committee reports to the main faculty search committee.

2015-2016, Mentor for 1st yr SIO Graduate Students.

2015, Representative of physical oceanography curricular group students in the committee for the Scripps Institution of Oceanography teaching award.

Honors & Awards

2015, Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Fellowhsip, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution 2011, Best BSc thesis in Oceanography, University of Sao Paulo

Skills

Programming

Python, C, Fortran 90, Shell-Script, Matlab, git, mercurial, markdown

Languages

English (fluent), Portuguese (native), Spanish (professional fluency)

Membership

American Geophysical Union, The Oceanography Society, NumFOCUS

Other interests

Data science, Scientific reproducibility, Free software, Open science, History and philosophy of science, Bossa Nova, Portuguese literature

References

William R. Young

Distinguished Professor of Oceanography, UC San Diego, wryoung@ucsd.edu

Sarah T. Gille

Professor of Oceanography, UC San Diego, sgille@ucsd.edu

Teresa K. Chereskin

Research Oceanographer and Senior Lecturer, UC San Diego, tchereskin@ucsd.edu

Myrl Hendershott

Professor of Oceanography, UC San Diego, mch@ucsd.edu